Dr Natalie Cooper

EMAIL: NATALIE.COOPER@NHM.AC.UK TWITTER: @NHCOOPER123

WEBPAGE: NHCOOPER123.GITHUB.IO

GOOGLE SCHOLAR PROFILE: http://goo.gl/ehLTgG figshare: http://goo.gl/F2dPGh

ORCID: 10000-0003-4919-8655 RESEARCHERID: I-7976-2012

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research sits at the interface between macroecology and macroevolution, and aims to understand broad-scale patterns of biodiversity. I use cutting-edge phylogenetic comparative methods, morphological data collected from museum specimens, phylogenies, ecological data, species geographic range maps, fossils and various larger databases, to investigate a variety of topics including the influence of competition on macroevolution, rates and modes of evolution, convergent evolution in various taxa (including tenrecs and river dolphins), macroevolutionary analyses with fossil and living species, responses of cetaceans to past and current climate change, and dinosaur morphological diversity. I regularly share the outputs of my research with the public through Natural History Museum events like Dinosnores, Science Uncovered and Museum Lates.

ACADEMIC CAREER

2015-present	Researcher
	Life Sciences (Vertebrates), Natural History Museum, London, UK.
2012-2015	Assistant Professor
	School of Natural Sciences, Trinity College Dublin, Ireland.
2010-2011	Postdoctoral Fellow
	Human Evolutionary Biology, Harvard University, USA.
2009-2010	Postdoctoral Associate
	Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Yale University, USA.

EDUCATION

2005-2009	Ph.D, Phylogenetic approaches for studying competition in mammals			
	Imperial College London & Institute of Zoology, London, UK.			
	Supervisor: Prof. Andy Purvis; Co-supervisor: Prof. Kate Jones			
2004-2005	M.Sc. (Distinction), Advanced Methods in Taxonomy and Biodiversity			
	Imperial College London & Natural History Museum, London, UK.			
2001-2004	B.Sc. (1st class honours), Biological Sciences			
	University of Exeter, UK.			

GRANTS AND AWARDS

BBSRC STARS Grant. Advancing computational and data literacy skills 2016 £42,738 schools for Life Scientists. Co-PI on Leverhulme Research Project Grant (PI: Andrea Waeschen- £350,090 2016 bach). Molecules meet fossils - an integrated approach to studying marine palaeodiversity. British Ecological Society funding for project A Whale of a Time: how 2015 £5,000 have changing human pressures through time affected the ecology of rorqual whales (Balaenopteridae). Society of Systematic Biologists (SSB) funding for symposium at Evo-\$4,000 lution 2014 on The Dark Side of Phylogenetic Comparative Methods. Marie Curie Career Integration Grant (CIG) for project Evolutionary €100,000 2012 Ecology and Fossil Primates. Irish Research Council Embark Initiative Postgraduate Scholarship for €72,000 project Convergent Evolution in Malagasy Tenrecs for Sive Finlay. Seessel Postdoctoral Fellowship for Innovative Research in Biological Sci- \$37,000 2009 ences.

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

2016	Organiser of BES Macroecology SIG Early Career Mentoring event, London.				
2016	Organiser of BES Macroecology SIG annual meeting, University of Oxford.				
2016	Organiser of London Vertebrate Researchers Meeting.				
2016	Member of Methods in Ecology & Evolution code archiving strategy group.				
2016-present	Organiser of cross-departmental NHM Macroevolution Journal club.				
2015-present	NHM Athena SWAN committee member.				
2015	PhD External Examiner, Kevin Arbuckle, University of Liverpool.				
2015-present	Associate Editor at Methods in Ecology & Evolution.				
2015-present	Deputy Secretary of BES Macroecology Special Interest Group committee.				
2014-present	Member of BES Publications Committee.				
2014	Assistant at BES Macroecology Software Carpentry workshop.				
2013-2015	Organiser of #MacroJC, a tri-continental online macroevolution journal club.				
2013-2015	Co-chair of School of Natural Sciences INTEGER and Athena SWAN Gender				
	Equality committees, achieving Bronze accreditation in 2015.				
2013-2015	Evolutionary Biology & Ecology seminar series organiser at TCD.				
2012-2015	Staff administrator and developer of the EcoEvo@TCD blog at TCD.				
2012-2015	Organiser of NERD club, a weekly Ecology and Evolution research group				
	meeting for staff and PhD students across the School of Natural Sciences at				
	TCD.				
2013	Organiser of "Spatial Analysis in R" workshop for BES Macroecology and				
	Computational Ecology Special Interest Groups.				
2013-present	Grant reviewer for UK Natural Environment Research Council (NERC).				
2013-present	resent Grant reviewer for Canadian National Science Foundation (NSERC).				
2012-present	Member of British Ecological Society (BES) including Macroecology Group.				
2013-present	ent Member of Society of Systematic Biologists.				

INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

2016	Evolution	Skeletons in the closet: using NHM collections for evolutionary re-
		search (poster)
2015	MEE	Methods in Ecology & Evolution 5th anniversary symposium: The
		limitations of PCMs (invited)
2014	Linnaean	Radiations & Extinctions meeting: Reproducibility in macroevolution
	Society	(invited).
2014	Evolution	The "Dark Side" of phylogenetic comparative methods (symposium).
2013	ESEB	Ecological correlates of extrinsic mortality in mammals and birds
		(poster).
2013	Evolution	Ecological correlates of extrinsic mortality in mammals and birds.
2012	Evolution	Host phylospecificity and parasite sharing in primates and humans.
2011	EEID	Methods for detecting phylogenetic host specificity in parasites
		(poster).
2010	Evolution	Phylogenetic niche conservatism in mammals.
2008	Evolution	A common pattern of overdispersion in mammalian assemblages.

INVITED SEMINARS

- 2016 Edward Grey Institute for Ornithology, University of Oxford.
- 2016 CMEC (Centre for Macroecology Evolution & Climate), University of Copenhagen, Denmark.
- 2015 Biological Sciences Seminars, University of Lausanne, Switzerland.
- 2015 LERN: London Evolutionary Research Network (guest speaker).
- 2015 BLAM: Biology at Lund Annual Postgraduate Symposium (plenary speaker). Lund University, Sweden.
- 2015 Bioscience Seminars, Dublin City University, Dublin.
- 2014 Biosciences Seminar Series, Swansea University.
- 2014 Centre for Ecology & Conservation Seminar Series, University of Exeter.
- 2014 Ecology, Evolution, Behaviour & Environmental Economics Seminar Series, Queens University, Belfast.
- 2014 Biology & Environmental Science Seminar Series, University College Dublin.
- 2013 Ecology & Environment Seminar Series, University of Southampton.
- 2013 Ecology, Evolution & Environment Seminar Series, University of Sheffield.
- 2013 Biological Sciences Seminar Series, University of Liverpool.
- 2013 Evolutionary Morphology (EvMorph) Seminar Series, University of Chicago.
- 2013 Earth & Environment Seminar Series, Trinity College Dublin.
- 2011 Museum of Comparative Zoology Seminar Series, Harvard University.

INVITED PANEL MEMBER FOR PANEL DISCUSSIONS

- 2016 Practical Tips for Reproducible Science. BES Macroecology Special Interest Group annual meeting, Oxford.
- 2015 The Future of Data Archiving. BES annual meeting, Edinburgh.
- 2015 The Future of the Publications Circus. EUMacro meeting, Copenhagen, Denmark.
- 2014 Applying for Postdoctoral Jobs. BES Macro meeting, Nottingham.

PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT AND OUTREACH

2016-present	Macro at the Museum blog.		
2016	Surviving cold weather, NHM Dinosnores for Kids.		
2016	Leading Ladies tour, NHM Lates.		
2016	Animal penises, NHM Dinosnores for Grownups.		
2015-2016	Science Uncovered at the Natural History Museum (participant).		
2014	Organiser of SoapBox Science Ireland - an outreach event featuring women		
	in science explaining their research in an interactive way.		
2014	Talk for Dublin University Zoological Society on Gender Inequality in Science		
	& the Media.		
Interviewed on "The Morning Edition" on RTE1 and "FutureProof"			
	sTalk FM about our paper <i>Dying without wings</i> . See press release here.		
2013	Arranged filming of Research Profiles for female staff and students as part		
	of the INTEGER Gender Equality project. My video is on my website.		
2013	Organised a Three Minute Thesis video competition for PhD students.		
2013 & 2014	Organiser and tour guide for Discover Research Dublin at the TCD Zoology		
	Museum, as part of European Researcher's Night.		
2013 & 2014	Presented a session on What can we learn from skeletons? for Transition Year		
	students (16-17 years).		
2013-2015	EcoEvo@TCD blog developer and contributor. The blog has had over 65,000		
	views and won Best Science & Technology blog in 2014 at the Irish Blog		
	Awards.		
2012-present	Active Twitter user (@nhcooper123) with over 2000 followers and over 8000		
	tweets.		
2013 & 2014	Blog post contributor at SoapBoxScience and Science Policy and Outreach		
	Online.		

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

POSTGE	RADU	J ATE ST	UDENT SUPERVISIO	N		
PhD	201	2-2015	Thomas Guillerme	Macroevolution in living	g & foss	sil TCD
species						
MSci	201	6-2017	Charlotte Page	Convergence in river dol	phins	UCL
MRes 2016		6	Dan Bell	Allometry in cetaceans		Imperial
MRes	201	6	Guillermo Gilbert	Biogeography of Galapagos birds		Imperial
MRes 2012-2015		2-2015	Sive Finlay	Morphological disparity in tenrecs		es TCD
MSc	201	3	Marta Capolei	Host phylospecificity in parasites		TCD
MSc	200	8	Paddy Brock	Co-supervised with And	y Purvis	Imperial
MSc	200	7	Peter Hayward	Co-supervised with And	y Purvis	Imperial
MSc	200	7	Jack Lighten	Co-supervised with And	y Purvis	Imperial
UNDERGRADUATE AND TAUGHT POSTGRADUATE						
2016		PGLS in	n theory and in R		MRes	UCL
2012-2015 Intro to		Intro to	Biodiversity, Evolution & the Environment		Year 1 TCD	
2012-2015 Compa		Compa	rative Physiology (Ve	ertebrate Biomechanics)	Year 3	TCD
2013-2015 Resear		Researc	ch Comprehension (m	nodule coordinator)	Year 4	TCD
2013-2014 Tropi		Tropica	l Ecology Field Cours	se	Year 4	TCD
2012-2015 Fina		Final Ye	ear Research Projects		Year 4	TCD
2009		Biodiversity & Conservation		Year 3	Imperial	
2012-20	014	Taxono	my & Systematics		MSc	TCD
POSTGRADUATE, POSTDOCS AND STAFF						
2016		BES Best Practiced for Code Archiving workshop			All -	
2014		Linnaean Society Radiations & Extinctions workshop			All -	
2013-2015		Compu	omputer Skills (LaTeX, R, git etc.)		All T	TCD
2013		Introdu	ction to R for the term	rified!	Staff T	TCD

JOURNAL REVIEWING

2012-2015 Transferable Skills at NERD club

workshop

2010-2011 R (& Statistics) Help Hour

2010-2012 AnthroTree Phylogenetic Comparative Methods

The American Naturalist, Animal Conservation, Biological Reviews, BMC Evolutionary Biology, Conservation Biology, Ecography, Ecology, Ecology and Evolution, Ecology Letters, Evolution, Global Ecology & Biogeography, International Journal of Primatology, Journal of Animal Ecology, Journal of Applied Ecology, Journal of Biogeography, Journal of Evolutionary Biology, Methods in Ecology & Evolution, Nature Communications, Nature Ecology & Evolution, Oecologia, Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society: B, PLoS One, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA, Proceedings of the Royal Society: B, Proceedings of the Royal Society: Interface, Trends in Ecology & Evolution.

All

All

All

TCD

Harvard

PUBLICATIONS LIST

I have 25 peer-reviewed papers in internationally recognised journals, one in press and one currently in review My h-index is 16 on Google Scholar and 13 on ISI Web of Science.

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

2016

Cooper, N., Thomas, G.H., & FitzJohn, R.G. 2016. Shedding light on the "Dark Side" of phylogenetic comparative methods. Methods in Ecology and Evolution. 7, 693699. doi: 10.1111/2041-210X.12533.

Guillerme, T. & Cooper, N. 2016. Assessment of available anatomical characters for linking living mammals to fossil taxa in phylogenetic analyses. Biology Letters. 12, 20151003. doi: 10.1098/rsbl.2015.1003.

Guillerme, T. & **Cooper**, **N.** 2016. Effects of missing data on topological inference using a Total Evidence approach. Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution. **94**, 146158. doi: 10.1016/j.ympev.2015.08.023. See summary here.

Cooper, N., Thomas, G.H., Venditti, C., Meade, A. & Freckleton, R.P. 2016. A cautionary note on the use of Ornstein Uhlenbeck models in macroevolutionary studies. Biological Journal of the Linnaean Society. **118**, 64-77. doi: 10.1111/bij.12701.

2015

Finlay, S. & **Cooper**, **N.** 2015. Morphological diversity in tenrecs (Afrosoricida, Tenrecidae): comparing tenrec skull diversity to their closest relatives. PeerJ. 3, e927. doi: 10.7717/peerj.927. See summary here.

Nunn, C.L., & Cooper, N. 2015. Investigating evolutionary lag using the species-pairs evolutionary lag test (SPELT). Evolution. 69, 245253. doi: 10.1111/evo.12520.

2014

Healy, K., Guillerme, T., Finlay, S., Kane, A., Kelly, S.B.A., McClean, D., Kelly, D.J., Donohue, I., Jackson, A.L., & Cooper, N. 2014. Ecology and mode-of-life explain lifespan variation in birds and mammals. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London Series B: Biological Sciences. 281, 20140298. doi: 10.1098/rspb.2014.0298. See summary here.

Kelly, S.B.A, Kelly, D.J., **Cooper, N.**, Bahrun, A., Analuddin, K. & Marples, N. 2014. Molecular and phenotypic data reveal a cryptic species (Aves: *Dicaeum*) from the unique and understudied Sulawesi region. PLoS ONE. **9**, e98694. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0098694. See summary here.

2013

Cooper, N., & Nunn, C.L. 2013. Identifying future zoonotic disease threats: Where are the gaps in our understanding of primate infectious diseases? Evolution, Medicine and Public Health. 2013, 26-37. doi: 10.1093/emph/eotoo1. See summary here.

Kamilar, J.M. & Cooper, N. 2013. Phylogenetic signal in primate behaviour, ecology, and life history. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London Series B: Biological Sciences. 368, 20120341. doi: 10.1098/rstb.2012.0341.

Healy, K., McNally, L., Ruxton, G.D., **Cooper, N.**, & Jackson, A.L. 2013. Metabolic rate and body size are linked with perception of temporal information. Animal Behaviour. **86**, 685-696. doi: 10.1016/j.anbehav.2013.06.018. **F1000 recommended**.

2012

Cooper, N., Griffin, R., Franz, M., Omotayo, M., & Nunn, C.L. 2012. Phylogenetic host specificity and understanding parasite sharing in primates. Ecology Letters. **15**, 1370-1377. doi: 10.1111/j.1461-0248.2012.01858.x. **F1000 recommended**.

Cooper, N., Kamilar, J.M., & Nunn, C.L. 2012. Host longevity and parasite species richness in mammals. PLoS ONE. 7, e42190. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0042190.

Davies, T.J., Cooper, N., Diniz Filho, J.A.F, Thomas, G.H. & Meiri, S. 2012. Using phylogenetic trees to test for character displacement: a model and an empirical example from a desert mammal community. Ecology. 93, S44-S51. doi: 10.1890/11-0400.1.

2011

Cooper, N., Freckleton, R.P. & Jetz, W. 2011. Phylogenetic conservatism of environmental niches in mammals. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London Series B: Biological Sciences. 278, 2384-2391. doi: 10.1098/rspb.2010.2207.

Freckleton, R.P., **Cooper, N.** & Jetz, W. 2011. Comparative methods as a statistical fix: the dangers of ignoring an evolutionary model. The American Naturalist. **178**, E10-E17. doi: 10.1086/660272.

Collen, B., McRae, L., Deinet, S., De Palma, A., Carranza, T., **Cooper, N.**, Loh, J. & Baillie, J.E.M. 2011. Predicting how populations decline to extinction. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London Series B: Biological Sciences. **366**, 2577-2586. doi: 10.1098/rstb.2011.0015.

2010

Cooper, N., Jetz, W. & Freckleton, R.P. 2010. Phylogenetic comparative approaches for studying niche conservatism. Journal of Evolutionary Biology. **23**, 2529-2539. doi: 10.1111/j.1420-9101.2010.02144.X.

Cooper, N. & Purvis, A. 2010. Body size evolution in mammals: complexity in tempo and mode. The American Naturalist. 175, 727-738. doi: 10.1111/j.1420-9101.2009.01714.x.

Belmaker, J., Cooper, N., Lee, T.M. & Wilman, H. 2010. Specialization and the road to academic success. Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment. 8, 514-515. All authors contributed equally. doi: 10.1890/10.WB.25.

2009

Cooper, N. & Purvis, A. 2009. What factors shape rates of phenotypic evolution? A comparative study of cranial morphology of four mammalian clades. Journal of Evolutionary Biology. **22**, 1024-1035. doi: 10.1111/j.1420-9101.2009.01714.X.

Bielby, J., Cardillo, M. **Cooper, N.**, & Purvis, A. 2009. Modeling extinction risk in multispecies data sets: phylogenetically independent contrasts versus decision trees. Biodiversity and Conservation. **19**, 113-127. doi: 10.1007/s10531-009-9709.0.

2008

Cooper, N., Rodriguez, J. & Purvis, A. 2008. A common tendency for phylogenetic overdispersion in mammalian assemblages. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London Series B: Biological Sciences. 275, 2031-2037. doi: 10.1098/rspb.2008.0420.

Cooper, N., Bielby, J., Thomas, G.H. & Purvis, A. 2008. Macroecology and extinction risk correlates of frogs. Global Ecology and Biogeography. 17, 211-221. doi: 10.1111/j.1466-8238.2007.00355.x.

Meiri, S., Cooper, N. & Purvis, A. 2008. The island rule: made to be broken? Proceedings of the Royal Society of London Series B: Biological Sciences. 275, 141-148. doi: 0.1098/rspb.2007.1056.

Bielby, J., **Cooper, N.**, Cunningham, A., Garner, T. & Purvis, A. 2008. Predicting susceptibility to future declines in the world's frogs. Conservation Letters. **1**, 82-90. doi: 10.1111/j.1755-263X.2008.00015.x.

NON PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Cooper, N. & Belmaker, J. 2010. Opinion: Habitat data resolution and the detection of species interactions. Frontiers of Biogeography. 2, 46.

Natalie Cooper